would get up an hour later in the mornings than the other animals, no
complaint was made about that, either.
By the autumn, the animals were tired, but happy.
They had had a hard year, and after the sale of part of the hay and corn, the
stores of food for the winter were none too plentiful.
But the windmill compensated for everything.
It was almost half built now.
After the harvest, there was a stretch of clear, dry weather, and the animals
toiled harder than ever, thinking it well worthwhile to plod to and fro all
day with blocks of stone if, by doing so, they could raise the walls another foot.
Boxer would even come out at nights and work for an hour or two on his own by
the light of the harvest moon.
In their spare moments, the animals would walk round and round the
half-finished mill, admiring the strength and perpendicularity of its
walls, and marveling that they should ever have been able to build anything so imposing.
Only old Benjamin refused to grow enthusiastic about the windmill, though,
as usual, he would utter nothing beyond the cryptic remark that "Donkeys live a long time."
November came with raging southwest winds.
Building had to stop because it was now too wet to mix the cement.
Finally, there came a night when the gale was so violent that the farm
buildings rocked on their foundations, and several tiles were blown off the roof of the barn.
The hens woke up squawking with terror because they had all dreamed
simultaneously of hearing a gun go off in the distance.
In the morning, the animals came out of their stalls to find that the flagstaff
had been blown down, and an elm tree at the foot of the orchard had been plucked
up like a radish.
They had just noticed this when a cry of despair broke from every animal's throat.
A terrible sight had met their eyes.
The windmill was in ruins.
With one accord, they dashed down to the spot.
Napoleon, who seldom moved out of a walk, raced ahead of them all.
Yes, there it lay, the fruit of all their struggles leveled to its
foundations. The stones they had broken and carried so laboriously scattered all around.
Unable at first to speak, they stood gazing mournfully at the litter of fallen stone.